Subs by thoughtnacht of Tron's L8 Fansubs
https://discord.gg/DRhKdaNaQq
Say it louder! Game?
He is B L K D, "Balakid" is how you read-
his name he came up with, containing 4 letters. Psh!
I will silence you, dumbass.
Until you're mute with a slice to your throat
Ya'll notice how his voice (tinig) is gone?
("pa tinig" a bit of a homophone of "patinig", patinig is Tagalog for vowel.)
(Lanzeta is trying to derive 2 meanings (voice and vowel) from the pa-ti-nig sound)
Let's make it so that his name will vanish
when I make his consonants (katinig) disappear!
("BLKD" is all consonants so his name will really be gone
if you remove all the consonants, the same applies for
the "Balakid" name derivation because
he removed all the vowels too from earlier)
Me? I'm still young, thats right. Ha!
They're all thinking that I don't respect my elders and-
that all of you are so old!
They're telling me that you are the standard?
They're forcing and squeezing in this narrative
but they don't realize until its too late
that death doesn't discriminate when it comes to age
Oh no! Ha!
He's in front of the one that will take him (to the afterlife)
Audaciously making a plan marked with a skull,
(this translation is very literal but I think he's just saying
verbosely that he's planning his death)
marked with bones (tatak buto) / he will run (tatakbo to)
when I'm filled with anger. And when this plan is done-
("ta-tak-bu-to" can have two meanings, tatak buto and tatakbo to)
The blood will spill and boil, and in time
the lake of blood will dry up
I'll take out a knife
stab and stab you till something spills out
nothing will be able to cover and hide you
after I'm done. You will be stepped on-
the street filled with trouble and mess.
Every step with intent to kill.
Your name is my angle. You're the obstacle?
(Balakid is Tagalog for obstacle)
When I run through you, there's nothing
that will stop my plan
And you're the "future" they say?
(BLKD was dubbed the future of Filipino rap battling)
I've designed a sharp scythe just for you
so its just right that-
You are the future and I am the present (mangyayari)
(Mangyayari can also mean 'to finish', in this context he will
be the one to finish BLKD)
There will be no obstacle when I go straight through
BLKD, block, obstacle?
And fuck, you're also a fence bro?
(He's enumerating words synonymous to balakid)
Knock knock? *Who's there*
I've climbed my way up to you
When I finally reach you,
you'll get butchered at your home
Then I'll catch a case. But I think there
is no wrong in doing a killing in this backyard.
He can't have me under control
You want to play with me?
Do you remember back when-
you battled someone dumb?
That's why you're battling me now,
someone from 'Gapo (Olonngapo)
(The city Lanzeta is from)
And this is your fault sir *pointing to Anygma*
Ha! So that you'll remember 2khelle when
you get swept by someone whack (bano)
(He's referencing BLKD's battle with 2khelle that BLKD lost.
2khelle is known as whack. Battlers from Olonggapo
are often chastised jokingly for being whack because of this)
'Clinging to a knife' is prevalent with us
BLKD was brought to us, and 'he' was served
You got cooked in 'Gapo-
(Cooked or "luto" in Tagalog can mean "rigged", he's pertaining
to BLKD's losing to 2khelle was rigged)
so that now they can have me eat you!
Alright, lets move on
How have you been, being poor and all?
Hey don't look away, that wasn't me making fun of you
Just like what Japormz did to Kahir, I'll spit on your face. Pweh!
(He's referencing a Fliptop battle where an MC spit on his opponent)
Remember what BLKD said? "This is a fight of crime and sedition"
"Miriam Defensor vs Rhyzza Mae Dizon"
(Miriam Defensor was a senator and a strong debater, and Rhyzza is a kid actor-comedian)
That's what you bring to a battle?
You (BLKD) keep saying "this is my creation", "that's my creation"
and you (the fans) are swayed by him?
You keep doing 'sumbat' and bringing up your contributions,
(Sumbat is when you constantly remind someone about something you’ve done for them to make them feel little)
These fans are easily impressed because they're shallow.
Now let me show you something, game?
One more time, game?
You remember you said "A shallow stab was done by Lanzeta"
(Lanzeta is actually a kind of knife)
So now I stab you, that's what Lanzeta did
So Bathala (God) forgive me
for what Lanzeta did, for what the lanzeta did, and for the maker of the lanzeta
(I'm actually not 100% sure what he really meant here)
So what are our similarities? Why do people compare you to me?
Is it in the way you create? Because your lines are deep?
Is it in the way you create? Where did it come from?
It came from Lanzeta, so you're made from Lanzeta / finished by Lanzeta
(Yari can both mean the make of something, or to finish)
Aren't you ashamed of yourself? Stealing and thieving?
This is what some people tell me, and I've noticed as well
So many have told me. No one needs to hear it from anyone else,
this one came from me!
(Another play on words, can mean both "straight from the horse's mouth" and "he came from me")
You perform your poetry, but where does your poetry come from?
I will slap that poetry onto your face that
came from me / got red because of me
(na-mu-la can be interpreted as "got red" or "it came from")
then I'll point a gun at you
will this guy be able to 'sumbat'? Bang!
This will go through this wall, its right that
it came from you / gun shot that came from you
(Tama can mean 'correct'. Or 'shot' in this context because of the gun setup from earlier)
If this guy is the basis, all of you should have yourselves checked
Come over here and I'll bring you to your maker
Look back from where you came from
until the maker takes you back
and then that'll be the time I return you to your maker
Because your intention is to steal something from me
When you look at it, your reflection in the water is deep,
its dark. You're drowned there because-
you're so well known, I'll rise you up / make you really popular this time
But I'll overtake you first, I'll put a hole in you. Baow!
Now you wont be rising up anymore
So, you're that known?
Compadre (pre) that's wrong.
This kid will break you.
He imitated in a patchy way.
Doing everything-
everyone will see him broken into parts
when he looks he'll see that he's in pieces,
shattered mirror.
Why? Is he the culprit?
When all of these MCs are criminals,
crimes of imitating others, no ones original.
Who are the MCs here that can really say they have a style of their own?
Answer!
Bitch please!
The truth will surface and seethe,
because all of them are too raw
They can't do what I do, even my screams
Even you BLKD (maging ikaw), you can't-
You can't even become yourself (maging ikaw),
now do your 'sumbat' repa (slang for compadre)
(Maging ikaw has two meanings, here in this line, and from the previous line)
I've overtaken these MCs, and they got surprised
Starting from a blank paper daubed with ink
And you're the pader (wall) that I wrote on,
binaboy na kita (I insulted you)
Is he really a pader (wall)?
This guy who's being idolized?
Heh, right I'm a durugista (drug addict)
A karit (scythe) and hammer, a symbol for
this communist
(BLKD is a known left-leaning activist so he's labelled as a communist)
Because you're poor right?
But nowadays he doesn't wear his glasses anymore, because he
now sees clearly / makes money
(BLKD wore glasses in his previous battles from way back,
Lanzeta is wittingly saying that BLKD now sees clearly and makes money.
"Kita" can mean sight or income here)
Before he was an activist, but now turned artista (actor),
named B L K D
Son of a whore, kapitalista! (capitalist)
(He's saying that its ironic that BLKD turned into a capitalist
now that he's earning money, while also pointing
out that he's also a 'capitalist' in the sense that his name is ALL CAPS)
So fall in line in the streets, bitch,
with the other whores.
His name that I'll bring down I'll step on
the ground where I want him
If you really are with the Kadamay
(A partylist in the PH for the poor,
kadamay also means 'someone who's with you in pain')
damay-damay (all of you will be together) in the destruction
of your home
umiyak kang walang tahanan
(then you'll sob without stopping / then you'll cry because you have no home)
('ta-ha-nan' here can both mean 'end of sobbing' and 'home')
ba-ba-ha-yang luha
(it will flood with your tears / your tears will be housed)
and the next time this guy burns another effigy,
(activists in the PH make effigies of hated politicians as a symbol of protest)
they'll all explode definitely, when I throw at them an open LPG!
(LPG is Liquid Petroleum Gas, its typically a meter high gas canister)
You can call me Mendiola Massacre!
(A well-known political killing in the PH)
and you've just lined up for me to be killed
I'm Bimby Aquino - Cojuanco
(He's referencing a popular child belonging from the Aquino - Cojuanco family,
the family that is known to be the culprit behind Mendiola Massacre.
And Lanzeta has been made fun for looking a lot like Bimby lol)
This is Hacienda Luisita!
(The site where the killings happened)
Basta 'Gapo bano? (If you're from Olonggapo you're a whack MC)
("Basta 'Gapo bano" is a commonly reiterated chant in Fliptop directing
playful resentment towards Olonggapo MCs. This started from when BLKD
was undeservingly defeated by 2khelle)
You still can't move on from that?
Oh Basta 'Gapo bano?
From where it all started, that's where it'll end
You can't handle that I'm mahangin? (boastfull)
Then keep that buried in your chest
This new design of lanzeta,
don't forget and keep it marked within your minds!
(Those last four lines is Lanzeta's signature ender to his battles)
Hey bata (kid)
You've just said that you're mahangin (boastful, full of air)
But your air, is just you bragging that can't be pacified
While my air is for the swaying of the flag
Because my voice is amihan (northeast monsoon winds),
the air I blow is habagat (southwest monsoon winds)
So bata (kid), no?
You we're a bata (flunkey) of 2khelle
That he himself was the flunkey of Nico
(Another Fliptop MC from Olonggapo)
Just from that, I should have two wins,
Why are you even here?
A kid that's aggresive?
Someone who kills people?
But weren't you just pushed around by a flunkey of Kardo?
(He's referring to Shernan a Fliptop MC turned actor in a hit TV
show in the PH where Kardo is the leading character.
Shernan also had real beef with Lanzeta)
But this kid isn't really lacking in years of experience,
he lacked in courage
gulang (age) doesn't matter that much,
but gulang (cunning) matters!
That's why your brutality in battle doesn't sell
I just proved this Lanzeta/lanzeta tiklop (folds)
(The lanzeta knife actually has a a mechanism that lets it fold itself,
so its fitting that he pointed out that Lanzeta the MC
also folds when being pushed around)
You're just a weapon for a fight
While I'm a weapon for war
You'll suddenly lie down dead on the BANG-keta (Bangketa is sidewalk)
The bullet is really pointed at the head
Bang! His skull will shake,
A downpour of blood
But this isn't Tokhang, that pretends that it doesn't know that innocents are killed
(Tokhang is a term for the anti-drug campaign in the PH where innocents are killed)
How would he fight back, someone who doesn't have the means to fight back?
(In Tokhang, the police usually says that suspects are killed
on the spot because they fought back, but this is not true most of the time
because outside investigations have proven that 'suspects'
didn't even fight back and had no means of fighting back.
BLKD makes a play on this by saying Lanzeta is a bit
similar to an innocent suspect, not because he couldn't fight back,
but because he didn't fight back, being a coward in his beef with Shernan)
So? Does it hurt? You can't accept that?
Ok then I'll make it more fair
This guy who's full of talent
The weapon that I'll use has an Illustrative form
Yes, lanzeta on Lanzeta,
saksakan (stabbing), sharp knife on sharp mind
Yes, lanzeta on saksakan (electrical outlet), it really is shocking
Even when it goes blank, my mind. You'll still have so many wounds.
(Notice he says blank-ang, this can also be Blanka ang
(Even when my mind goes Blanka), he's referencing Blanka
from Street Fighter who has electrical abilities,
hence the 'shocking' setup from earlier )
So how would your blade stand me? When the chainsaw from before wasn't effective?
(He's referencing his past opponent Tipsy D who has a signature chainsaw bar)
You're just making it difficult for yourself,
a poor guy who approves of the TRAIN Law
(The TRAIN Law has increased taxes in the PH which in
turn has made commodities more expensive
thus making it even harder for the poor)
How would a lanzeta cut Vic Von Doom?
(Victor Von Doom is a Marvel villain that has titanium armor.
This could also be a nod to MF DOOM because BLKD has referenced him before)
Its only useless threats, the ramblings of Kim Jong Un
(Lanzeta does look a bit like North Korea's leader lol)
I'm from the future of battle rap of the year 3030
So its clearer than 20/20
That your condition now is 50/50
You're fierce, I admit
But only just in rap
I thought you were a bata with a 'K'
(When he says 'K' he means a bata with 'kaya', a kid who is determined)
I was wrong, you're just a batak (addict)
(a play on bata plus 'K', also relevant that Lanzeta
is often accused of using drugs by his opponents)
Just some trip, he got obsessed in the play of pantig (syllables)
You have so many multi-syllabic rhymes and wordplays
But you don't perform in any gigs
You're only focusing on deep lyricism in all your attacks
Hey, it's only Invictus now who understands you
(Invictus is another Olonggapo MC who also has deep lyricism)
Yes its true that you are a strong MC
But its showing on the outside that you are weak
Because what is being deep good for if its not effective in battle?
I'm a balakid (obstacle) that symbolizes your dedication
Because the true obstacle is your own limitations
My mission is to bring forth evolution
So my defeat against you, is still my victory
Wrecked!
Me, I'm true to this culture, I'm true to this art form.
For me, Lanzeta should have won, but thanks for the win anyways