Subs by thoughtnacht of Tron's L8 Fansubs
https://discord.gg/DRhKdaNaQq
Check, CHECK, CHIEECKK
I will be calm only for now
The applause is louder
A child moth who flirted with a dancing red flower
His battle in Cebu (The city where GL's last battle happened)
To a monster, he compared himself
but when you rap you look like a kid goat with a cold that also got rained on
He had glasses on and his haired was tied up
You look like a desperate maestro (teacher) that is a bayot (gay)
YOU DON'T FRIGHTEN ANYONE
I will only be scared if you offer me "150"
(150 is a known slang for a gay man offering 150 pesos to suck you off)
You're raw, kid
Wipe off the drool from your face first
You look like the youngest sibling that gets beaten up by the oldest
Your voice is horrible,
the mark of a loser
Every time you shout in a battle, you look like a kid that got his toy stolen
AFTER I GOT DONE WITH DOSAGE
(Dosage was his previous battle)
I was content,
really peaceful
They had me battle you so I can learn to be humble
Your play on words cannot be understood,
too modern, too complicated, and nothing meaningful is being said.
Here I'll teach you,
but you will need to pay me
If you shake hands with me,
the lines in your palm will change / your destiny will change
My brain is like a world, chaotic, and is
tagilid (crazy / tilted)
(Tagilid can be interpreted as crazy as in a crazy person,
and tilted like how the earth spins)
I'm the horrible smell that seethes from hole in your psyche,
you should listen to me.
The thorns are thick, what's inside this that's flowing?
Venom that came from the roots of cursed trees,
it's so vast and thick here that you can't distinguish illusion from reality.
What you see outside is the reflection of the emotions inside you.
You saw a soldier holding a spear and you are the one he will stab
But then the soldier you saw was actually just a tree and some vines
Accompanied by the shadows of your past
The solid concrete that you can lean on is pretending to be asleep
The real answers are hidden inside me
So close your eyes, don't listen to the noises that bring fear and anxiety
Know yourself, the you that's behind the clustered voices
The real me cannot be explained by the mind
If you want to follow me, the first key is mushrooms
On the other way is regret, here success is at the end
Do not dictate, and do not judge me
I see the world in my own way
Your eye will be opened so that your mouth will close
You are an infant, before you learn to speak, you must first learn to listen
And you will be found again after you leave
If everything has an end, your journey will eventually arrive at its destination
Order in the court, your honor, and the jury,
and to those who were anticipating this match-up
I want to ask for your forgiveness, I'm sorry
Because I will break the theme
This is not a fight nor war,
this is a trial
for a fake prophet, the accused is Lucas
Hailing from Cagayan De Oro (Zend Luke's city)
the new big fish that everyone's been talking about,
the one who will inherit the throne,
a beast in the sea, yes
but you have been washed away by the waves
so this fish is simply dead in the 6 minutes of his ahon, game?
(Ahon means 'ascend', typically used when ascending from the ocean.
Ahon is also the name of this FlipTop event so GL is asking
the crowd if the Ahon audience is game. Also relevant that FlipTop
usually gives MCs 2 minutes per round, 6 minutes in total for the whole battle.)
Because they say that you've just made it
into the starting 5 lineup of Mindanao
(Mindanao is one of the three main islands of PH and FlipTop has a
Mindano division full of talentend MCs)
they say you're the greatest of your batch
like Fukuda of Ryonan
(Slam Dunk series reference, also there is a Mindanao MC named Fukuda)
they say you're the latest of your class
your ink is of a different class
so I congratulate your pen game
you're the new ink of Aric, because the tats/Tatz is already faded
(Aric is Anygma's first name, Anygma is the founder of FlipTop
and Uprising Records, he also has tattoos.
Tatz or Tatz Maven is a FlipTop MC who is also in Uprising Records)
Yes, a substitute of the Maven.
You should be aware of that
Sixth threat? No, sixth man, that's your contribution
(Sixth Threat is a FlipTop MC on the supposed starting 5 of Mindanao)
Yep you're just a reserve on the bench boy, so Sak I hope you realize
(Sak Maestro is another MC in the supposed starting 5)
that the bench literally got carried
but they say that you're the deep lyricist
that is easy to get (easy to understand)?
Deep? That is easy to get?
Meaning, your existence has a shattered form
Just like a floatie that drowned
Or a fire extinguisher that burned
Or like Aklas that sleeps, you get it?
(Aklas was a FlipTop MC who is made fun for doing so much cocaine
that he never gets to sleep)
You're smart, but the points you try to get across fail
You're like a lawyer who turned to Tulfo
(Tulfo is a host in a TV show who tries to help people with cases,
just like in the show Judge Judy, but Tulfo isn't an actual law practicioner)
But seriously, deep that is easy to get? Wow!
That just means your style is watered down
Kjah, Kial, Ilaya, the ones who are fighting for something,
(He's enumerating FlipTop MCs who can be said are left field)
who can sacrifice entertainment, while you,
you are the most normal from the most crazy/left-field
Because you said, "I am a messiah, I am a reincarnation"
"I am a demi-god", you're just putting yourself up on a pedestal
until you make a mess at the top
If Emar is Industry, then you are the smoke
(Emar Industriya is another MC that is of the left field)
"I am as vast as nothingness", "I am as old as the universe"
You're always putting yourself first, in every verse you vomit out
Looking at his image in the river, that's how narcissist Lucas is.
But the waves are already polluted, that's why you dont get it
You thought your reflection is what you see in the water,
but actually its trash
And then he always screams about dreams and imagination
If the presence is gorging, it is hungry for attention
So even if you are great in projecting yourself,
and you provide no lesson or insight,
you won't be able to wake the masses, if your projection is astral
So what now? Wasn't that direct to your chest?
No bars that are lackluster, thats how you emphasize
And for the jury, it would be good if you try to notice-
Count how many times he will mention "me", "me"
And to prove that he is sinful, this is my evidence,
now I call the accused for his defense
Squeezed through the eye of a needle in the grass
The entryway is hidden and very hard to find
Everything has an end, this journey will reach its destination eventually
And in your leaving, the only thing I want for you to bring for me-
is your second death!
My stomach is growling from the
smell of alimuom (vapor rising from the ground, typically after a rain)
The bridge for you to walk toward the next life,
is the one I'll cross to satisfy my hunger
You said that MCs in Visayas are scared of you?
Yes that's right you are scary
So cute, the result? You lost in your first battle
You're boastful? I'm floating / high
in the air, never faltering
its so easy for me to step on your head that's mahangin (full of air)
(Aside from being full of air, "mahangin" can also mean being boastful)
based on what you've shown, in summary you are weak
this is the fruit of your every inconcrete word (bulaang salita or words like bubble)
that's why your tounge is slippery
("madulas na dila" here is close to someone
who is prone to say things they aren't supposed to)
Now you should listen here, those who are like you
are typical, there is nothing special about you
You think you are lyrical just because you've learned how to be technical?
You just wanted to fit in, you had no intention to
measure the distance
What you have been doing is already being done by all
Let's just say that you're great in the style so old and used by some
In other words, your contribution will only be leftovers
You don't have a mark you can call your own
Your whole being is a debt, you will easily be blown away by the wind
Your papel ('paper' literally, but can mean 'role') in life will easily be forgotten
Too much confidence, you wanted to be among the parade
You got naked and strewn about, but you didn't know that this is a masquerade
Blind to the light guided by the lamp,
intelligently speaking is the mouth of the cave that you just entered
In this world, the lies and truths both mean the same
You think you're skilled? Whereas you don't know anything about how things are
The mundane to the unusual is unusual to the mundane
I'm watching your little mind playing around
No discipline and respect, even the veterans you belittled
In the Visayas division you challenged and called out a lot of MCs
Now you're surprised to see me? Like an engkanto (a spirit in PH folklore) suddenly appearing?
Didn't you know? That its not good to mention names in gubat!
(Gubat can literally mean forest, and Gubat is the FlipTop event that is held in Visayas)
(It is bad omen to mention names or point fingers in the forest
because engkantos will appear.
It is relevant that GL called out a lot of names in the Gubat event)
I hope you get the messages I'm trying to convey,
I will force in a vast imagination into a narrow understanding
Your head is big, you're too arrogant.
Do you know this story?
A pretentious hunter that got played with by the elements
You're here in the thick of it, so watch your mouth
There is misfortune waiting at your every word
You think you're smart? Courageous? That's what you think of yourself?
Yeah sure that's fine. When you have a solid belief, you are easy to fool.
Guest.
Guilty your honor finally
Lucas has been imprisoned in a vicious system
You want some advice on how to get out?
Then don't miss out because for you there is a "tip si Batas" / Tipsy-Batas
("tip si Batas" in this context means Batas has a tip for him.
Batas is a FlipTop MC that has a later battle with another MC,
Tipsy D, in this same FlipTop event that GL is referencing.
And it also relevant that "batas" the word literally means "law")
So your honor, I'm done with the theme
Let's go back to war, since that is my forte
So its fitting that Zend Luke is shattered
Now that he's no longer in "korte"
(Korte here can both mean "court" as in court of law, and "form"
or "original shape" as in something won't be in korte after being broken/shattered)
Because, you're weird
He is very amazed at the ironies of the world
He's the kind of person that talks to himself
but doesn't even listen
Remember he said, "I'm aroused by the naked truth"
Nice, great move
But wait dude
does that mean that you are romantically excited by fake news?
And another thing he said, "I want to get destiny pregnant"
You want to get destiny pregnant?
Wow how wild, of a different class is your style
So what would your child be called?
Destiny's Child?
(Beyonce's group)
But wait, lets go back to top tier bars
Because to jokes I say no sir
I didn't go to Manila to be seen me-jo-ker
(me-jo-ker in this context can be "may joker" in that he doesn't want there to be seen a joker,
another can be "mediocre", he doesn't want to be seen as medicore)
Another one of his lines, "The flame is sinful if the water is clean"
Boom! The crowd went to sleep
the stars awoken
Boom!
His opponent got hit directly /s
But wait, its a pleasure to listen to
But in a battle, lame, trash
So its straight facts
Zend, look
wake up
this isn't fake class,
I've brought a great axe
while you brought paintbrush?
You went over here, so that your poetry can be heard
While I went over here to make you foam at the mouth
Like the President of America, this bastard is egotistical
being arrogant and ignorant
that's his trump card
You're unorthodox? Ha? Unorthodox really?
But why are your skills traditional?
The left field became right-wing so he's seen as self centered
I have a solid foundation, while your backbone's fractured
Yes, you're abstract because scattered around is your structure
Failed angles are what this dumb fuck's always looks for
How would your trip go further, if
("trip" in slang is something that someone craves to do)
ang-gu-long bu-tas
(can both mean "tires have holes" and "angles have holes")
And he's always full of swagger, fake swagger
Sometimes maxed out anger
then suddenly ok and calm for a bit
that's how lodi is with his trips
("lodi" is slang for idol, its idol backwards.
"trip" in slang is something that someone craves to do)
so I'm sorry, thats cheap
so that's why you're from CDO
because your beef is corny
(Zend Luke comes from the city of CDO/Cagayan De Oro, and in the PH
there is also a brand of canned goods called CDO that are well-known
for their corned beef)
So that's why this generic is generic, this is our comment
his poetry has no punch, because it comes from spoken
(spoken poetry)
not for his opponent, disconnected, broken
ya'll think the message is received?
then you're fucking wrong Zend/send
have you ever seen how the moon and sun make love to each other?
I have
Smile of a dog that sings on February 30, out of tune
("Smile like a dog's" is an idiom meaning a smile that has bad intentions behind it)
My deluge brings energy that is of a different class
Power of a storm/typhoon with a third eye
Your journey will now end tonight
Your cold body will be the only one that is left
Your expertise will remain as a shadow of someone else
The shape of the jungle won't change if you are gone
Thirsty and hungry, Christ's body was given to you
a lost spirit just like St. Elmo's Fire
because you are of old, you have become mundane they said
When everyone looks at you no one's perception will change
When our writtens are weighed, you will shatter completely
my bars will make one's chest heavy like jealousy
This is a lineup of stars, a constellation is formed
Just look if you please, I will stay bright in the telescopes of true pilosopo (intelligent people)
Carefully chosen themes and concepts have become the signature
This is not just finding fault or being rude
This is literature!
Your skills won't advance anymore
even if you train and a lot of time has passed
that will only stay right there like yesterday
we both have fire inherited from the first creators
I want to share light
You want to burn trash
My soul becomes naked once I walk on the stage
I pour everything in just to make the glass even wider
Possibility is vast, there is no limitation that is potential
Obstacles are only illusions
Everything will pass but not everything has an end
I'm farther and taller than the ones that you wish for
My style isn't really new,
this was already created in the future
My written has an inviting summary
will make anyone exorbitantly obsessive like a girl with curls
Even though the age does not show in the intelligence,
they say there is a lack in real experience
My spirit/ghost writer, is the ghost of my past life
I don't know what you see, like the memories of someone blind
you will keep coming back to it like a promise that was broken
even if you forcefully reach the victory that is destined to be mine
just like the word apologize, you can't do anything
I bring time and tears, every drop counts
I'm like tears, difficult to stop
I'm really only here to offer a hand
Follow the message, not the messenger
because he will continue on his personal journey,
thank you very much and good bye to you all
Is this Zend Luke? The champion of FlipTop tryouts?
Oh shit! I watched your freestyle. Bro, lit!
So sick!
Off beat!
Yes you fell down on how it goes down
No form in the formula utilized
No rhythm in the algorithm
In the tempo, temporary
Because he said, he has his own rhythm
He even made excuses, disrespecting Supreme Fist (The DJ)
They say that I should not use the "Train of Thought"
(GL's signature style)
Because you people might not get it
But I don't give a shit as long as my opponent dies.
Game?
Let's start it with Genesis, Cain and Abel? No
Too overused, that part
I'm a beast, an animal that eats its pair
I'm a cannibal in Noah's Ark
Noah's Ark, it will rain, it will rain bullets now
and its gonna flood son, with my handgun
now your end's near, you'll think its Wish Bus, with so much
click here, click here, click here, click here
(Wish 107.5 a popular radio station has a segment "Wish Bus"
that showcases in YouTube videos different artists in the PH,
their outro in these videos has these artists say "click here" numerous times
indicating the subscribe button to ther channel)
that's how you subscribe
to a magazine, so fast I trigger,
this guy won't reach St. Lukes,
(St. Lukes is a popular hospital)
straight to St. Peter he'll go.
(St. Peter is a popular funerarial establishment)
Peter? Parker, Spiderman
In the web he lies, he's caught
But I thought you were clean?
Then why you always on Mary Jane?
What's the advantage of Zend-
"daya" only
(He's trying to reference Zendaya here, the actress for MJ in the recent Spiderman
"daya" also means cheat, he's trying to also say that cheating is
Zend Luke's only advantage)
I'm nervous here in Manila well as you can see
The Train of Thought suddenly stopped, just like the MRT
(MRT is the Metro Rail Transit, trains that run on Manila, known for its many issues
that inconvenience passengers)
Now I'll go crazy, you should feel the desperation
I didn't "trip" Doc Pau
(He didn't like Doc Pau, or maybe he didn't like how he lost to Doc Pau?
Doc Pau was his previous battle)
so I skipped my medication
This guy just pretends to be crazy, but people call him 'different' already
Is he the new generation? You're only average when it comes to stats
Too much standard deviation
I exposed his verses, and now you know the limitations
since I studied Zend like meditation
I opened up his secret, bible-explanation like
Burned, the Gospel of Luke
No more revelation
I ascended so my opponent will drown
I don't care about the judging
That's how you devour, brad (brother)
Downed, this modern "balagtasan"
(A form of debate done in rhymes. Its quite an old tradition
that people like to compare with FlipTop and rap battling as a whole)
by classic battle rap!
ez, and you still have a round thre-
and you still have a next battle, no one will listen to you anymore
you were unfortunate Lucas because you faced me,
gg